{
  "reference_number": "9980",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "This is the most realistic approach and much more likely to gain widespread acceptance because it provides a reasonable pathway\n\n for the agricultural sector. However, I believe that a reduction in the levels of short lived gas emission must still be a part of the target\n because we must aim for a scientifically acceptable stable climate at an acceptable temperature."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "I am not too well versed in the ETS, but in its current iteration it is not doing a particularly good job at reducing emissions because\n cheap credits can be imported (as well as other reasons). I also believe that New Zealand should achieve 'true' carbon neutrality, as\n\n opposed to having to rely on carbon credit imports."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Locking ourselves in to a target 30 years away is absurd. New information obtained, as well as the future effects of climate change,\n mean that the context we set the target in today is bound to be different when 2050 comes around. We may need to set a more or\n\n less ambitious target for any number of reasons."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The budgets have the potential to have big social and economic impacts which can be hard to foresee, especially when the\n\ncircumstances for New Zealand change. We need to be flexible so that we can work around issues that arise."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The socioeconomic impacts in particular should be a strong consideration, and I believe we must have a plan to mitigate the potential\n\nfor fuel poverty."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Cant have a goal without a plan!"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I believe that the Climate Change Commission should play a key role in advising the government. This is because it will be\n\nindependent, ensuring that realistic and fair targets are set whilst being able to hold governments to account. The process should be\ntransparent and justified. In particular, I believe there is huge potential for New Zealand to become a world innovator in emerging\n\ntechnologies which can help climate change. New Zealand has always been a technological innovator and fighting fighting climate\nchange can be seen as an opportunity. As before, I also believe we must have a plan to mitigate the potential for emission budgets to\n\ncause fuel poverty."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "I believe the ETS is flawed as it allocates far too many credits and does not provide a particularly meaningful incentive to reduce\n\nemissions. However, I also do not believe that an independent body should be able to decide how many credits are available or\nallocated because these bodies are harder to publicly hold to account. Public discussion needs to be had about how and where the\nETS fits into the Carbon Zero goal, in particular concerning the agricultural sector."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
